<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rebels text opened, and their solemn appeal answered being a sermon preach'd in the parish church of Up-Lime, on the thanksgiving-day for our wonderful deliverance from the late horrid rebellion, being Sunday, July 26. 1685 / by Charles Hutton ...</title>
            <author>Hutton, Charles, b. 1652 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12417979</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12417979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 943:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rebels text opened, and their solemn appeal answered being a sermon preach'd in the parish church of Up-Lime, on the thanksgiving-day for our wonderful deliverance from the late horrid rebellion, being Sunday, July 26. 1685 / by Charles Hutton ...</title>
                  <author>Hutton, Charles, b. 1652 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61759:1"/>
            <p>THE REBELS TEXT OPENED, AND THEIR Solemn Appeal ANSWERED.</p>
            <p>Being a SERMON Preach'd in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Up-Lime,</hi> on the Thankſgiving-Day for our Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Deliverance from the late <hi>Horrid Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being <hi>Sunday, July</hi> 26. 1685.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CHARLES H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTON,</hi> A. M. and Rector of the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Accipe nunc Danaûm inſidias, &amp; crimine ab uno Diſce omnes.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Aen. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Biſhop's Head</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61759:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>John Cotton</hi> of <hi>Botheraux</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> Knight, and one of His Majeſtie's Juſtices of the Peace for that County.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Sermon you were pleas'd to deſire a Copy of, and others ſince commanded me to Print it: I have now gratified both, and run the riſque of publick cenſures, which yet I expect from none but the diſſenting and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Party: and thoſe I as much deſpiſe as they do Government. If it be a crime to Preach up Loyalty to God, and the King, in an age wherein there are ſuch numerous and daring Rebels to both; I muſt confeſs my ſelf guilty of it: but ſhall not ask pardon of them, till they beg theirs from God, and repent of this great ſin, which (like Witches, to whom they are compared) 'tis doubtful whether they will ever do. However to leave ſuch among us without excuſe, this Sermon with ſome little alterations has already viſited other Churches and Counties beſides my own, and is now like to viſit more; that if poſſible, the Antidote may be as diffuſive as the Poiſon: yet how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb facs="tcp:61759:3"/>
it quite, whether by making new Laws, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reviving the old, and putting them in a vigorous execution, is humbly ſubmitted to the wiſdom of the preſent Parliament; from whoſe united Heads, and Hearts, and Hands, we now hope for, and almoſt promiſe our ſelves a perfect Cure. And I am confident you will not be wanting in your Sphere to contribute what you can towards it; you, who ſtood ſo firm to the Church, and Crown, amidſt thoſe black and diſmal ſtorms that formerly clouded, and eclipſed both; and have ever ſince, even when things ran high again in favour of Rebellion, and once more threatned ruine to our antient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and Epiſcopacy, preſerv'd your Integrity, and Loyalty intire: which therefore together with your Charity and Hoſpitality (Vertues that are natural to your Family) without doubt you will carry with you to your Grave; as thoſe will carry you farther, even to the regions of Bliſs and Immortality: where that you may late, and ſafely arrive, is the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble Servant, and obliged Kinſman,</hi> Charles Hutton.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-Lime
<date>October <hi>24. 1685.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61759:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOSHUA xxii. 22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord God of gods, the Lord God of gods, he knows, and Iſrael be ſhall know, if it be in rebellion, or if in tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, (ſave us not this day.)</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is the unhappy Fate of the Holy Scriptures to be abuſed into a kind of publick Armory, whence the ſeveral contending Parties of the Chriſtian World fetch Weapons to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and fight each other; no Sect is ſo profligate, no not that which perverts Faith into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Religion into Rebellion, but has recourſe to the Sacred Bible to palliate and juſtifie their impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions: Neither is this ſome new thing not heard of in former Ages; ſince we find it practis'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſixteen hundred years ago by the grand Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the World: He would fain have perſwaded the Bleſſed Jeſus to have thrown himſelf headlong from the lofty Temple, on preſumption the good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels would miraculouſly interpoſe, and prevent all danger in his Fall: And this he prov'd our Saviour might lawfully do, from a diſtorted Paſſage of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Pſalms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11, 12. And Satan has always
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61759:4"/>
had, and ſtill has his Agents and Emiſſaries, that uſe the ſame Deviliſh Policy. This they were at in <hi>Forty two,</hi> and, God knows, play'd it then with too great ſucceſs: And though ſome of thoſe are long ſince dead, and gone to their own place; yet, as if there were a tranſmigration of Souls, and they did live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in their preſent Succeſſors, the ſame evil Spirit is conjur'd up again, and appears in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mantle; there being men found in our days, who, though in open and actual Rebellion againſt God and the King, and involv'd in all thoſe crimes that horrid Sin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, had nevertheleſs the impudence to <hi>appeal to Heaven for the juſtice of their Arms, and to challenge God to decide for them in the Day of Battel.</hi> And this plainly appears by a Clauſe in their late <hi>bloudy and blaſphemous Declaration;</hi> in the Cloſe of which, thoſe very words I juſt now repeated, as near as I can remember them, are inſerted: and it is further confirmed, <hi>by their inſiſting on this very Text,</hi> as I am credibly informed, <hi>the Day before the Battel.</hi> Now ſince this their <hi>ſolemn Appeal has been anſwer'd from Heaven in a moſt ſolemn and ſtupendious manner, and God has decided againſt them to their intire Defeat, and total Overthrow;</hi> I know no place of Scripture fitter to be inſiſted on at this time: partly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm ſome of you in your unſhaken Loyalty, and to convince others that waver'd in it; and partly to clear the Text from thoſe corrupt Gloſſes, falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and fallacious Inferences, which Rebel and Army Preachers have raiſed from it: And that I may do this effectually, I ſhall give you the real Occaſion, natural Diviſion, and genuine Application of the Words.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61759:4"/>Firſt, For the real occaſion of theſe words, and that was this; <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord, and Ruler of his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after he had conducted them ſafe from <hi>Egypt</hi> to the borders of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and cut his paſſage thither, through continual Miracles, Victories, and Succeſſes, being conſcious to himſelf of his great Age, and warn'd from Heaven of his approaching Fate, by Gods command adopts <hi>Joſhua</hi> into the Copartnerſhip of his royal Government, that it might ſit more eaſie on his ſhoulders, when he came to bear it all, which he muſt do after his death, <hi>Num.</hi> 27.20. and withal among many other excellent inſtructions how to govern that ſtubborn and rebellious people, he gives him ſome relating to the diviſion of the promiſed Land among the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tribes, willing him to obſerve this method in making it: The <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> ſhould take up their habitation in <hi>Gilead,</hi> and <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and other adjacent Countries, which lay on this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> becauſe they had been very importunate to fix their abode there, and for their good ſervices he had granted it; but 'twas on this condition, that they continued to aſſiſt their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in conquering the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and when that was done, and that Land divided between the other nine Tribes and half, theſe two Tribes and half might return, and dwell in the Countries which themſelves firſt choſe, <hi>Num.</hi> 32.29, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> accordingly after <hi>Moſes</hi> had reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his meek and righteous Soul unto God, and his reverend and aged body was interr'd by Him in ſome obſcure and unknown grave, leſt the giddy multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that ſo often murmur'd againſt him whilſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, ſhould, now he was dead, repent of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61759:5"/>
inſolent behaviour, and to compenſate for it, worſhip his aſhes, and adore his very duſt: after this (I ſay) he that was before his Partner, and now his Succeſſour, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> having finiſht his Conqueſt of the Holy Land, and divided it among the nine Tribes and half; purſuant to the inſtructions of his dying Predeceſſour, diſmiſſes the two other Tribes and half, giving them their deſerved praiſe and commendation, and ſeaſonable advice to ſerve the great God, who had proſper'd their Arms, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them reſt from all their Enemies; and withal full power and commiſſion to return and dwell in their wiſht for, choſen, and promiſed poſſeſſion, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> 22.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now in their journey homeward, theſe two Tribes and half, as they paſſed by the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſet up a great Altar there; not one deſtin'd for Sacrifice or Oblation, but an Altar of remembrance to ſucceeding Ages, that they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and ador'd the ſame God which <hi>Iſrael</hi> did; and had as much right as they to come and worſhip at <hi>Shiloh,</hi> the place where Gods honour dwelt, and where his Service was moſt ſolemnly perform'd, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. but this made ſo great a noiſe, that it alarm'd their Brethren the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and cauſed them to think of revenging this innovation by ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing them on it, who firſt built this Altar; for a new Altar they thought beſpoke a new Religion, and all thoſe Schiſmaticks and Separatiſts that had a hand in it: and therefore they are for reducing them to order and conformity, by outward compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and force; and to this end reſolve to make War upon them, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but before they proceed to this extremity (which is commonly, or ought to be, the laſt, and never uſed but in caſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61759:5"/>
neceſſity) they ſent ſelected Meſſengers from every Tribe, to demand the reaſon of this proceeding; and why they had erected an Altar (as it were) in defiance to that at <hi>Shiloh:</hi> if they were prejudiced againſt their Country, becauſe it had not the viſible Symbols of God's ſpecial Preſence in it, as <hi>Canaan</hi> had, they were content theſe two Tribes and a half ſhould come and dwell among them, although they themſelves were ſtraitned by it, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding if the land of your poſſeſſion be unclean, then paſs ye over unto the land of the poſſeſſion of the Lord, wherein the Lord's Tabernacle dwelleth, and take poſſeſſion among us: but rebel not againſt the Lord, nor rebel againſt us in building you an Altar, beſides the Altar of the Lord.</hi> They would endure any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, rather than ſuffer a Schiſm or Separation to happen among them. Now to this heavy Charge, the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeh,</hi> plead <hi>Not guilty;</hi> and ſolemnly proteſt before God, who ſearcheth the hearts, That they had no other deſign in rearing this Altar, than the making it a Memorial for Poſterity to underſtand that they were Worſhippers of the ſame God, and ought to partake of the ſame Eccleſiaſtical Priviledges that their Brethren enjoyed that dwelt in the Holy Land. This was the true account of themſelves and their Proceedings; and if their incenſed Brethren would not believe it, nor any thing ſatisfie their boiling rage but their utter extirpation, all that they had left, and was lawful for them to do, was to <hi>invoke the God of Heaven, who is the great Protector of the innocent, to defend them from their Brethrens undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved wrath, or at leaſt ſo far to mitigate and appeaſe it, that they might be delivered from the dire effects
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61759:6"/>
thereof. The Lord God of gods,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the Words I ſhall conſider theſe three Parts:
<list>
                  <item>I. A publick Declaration of the Sovereign Power and Majeſty of God, That he is Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient and Omnipreſent, the ſupreme Lord, Governour and Judge of the whole World, <hi>The Lord God of gods,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>II. A Solemn Appeal to this ſupreme Lord, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and Judge, for the Equity of their Proceedings; they deſire help and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from him upon theſe and no other terms, That they were not in Rebellion or Tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, <hi>The Lord God of gods, he knows,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>III. A Suppoſition, That if they were Rebels, the Lord would not ſave them, <hi>If it be in rebellion, or if in tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, ſave us not this day.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. A publick Declaration of the Sovereign Power and Majeſty of God, That he is Omniſcient and Omnipreſent, the ſupreme Lord, Governour and Judge of the whole World, <hi>The Lord God of gods,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All the Power and Majeſty of Kings and Princes, of the high and mighty Men of the Earth, are but ſo many Streams and Rivulets that flow from this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal and inexhauſtible Spring; they are but ſo many Beams and Rays darted from this <hi>Almighty Sun, the Father of Lights, with whom there is no variable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſhadow of turning,</hi> James 1.17. All the Knowledge and Wiſdom of the ſubtileſt Politicians, the profoundeſt Divines, the acuteſt Philoſophers, and the learnedeſt Councellours, are but ſo many
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61759:6"/>
Particles of that <hi>infinite and boundleſs underſtanding, of that eternal and ubiquitary Soul</hi> (if I may ſo ſtyle the Divine Eſſence) from whence theſe intelligent and diſcerning Faculties proceed: And though for their Knowledge and Wiſdom, as well as Power and Majeſty, Men may be ſaid to be Gods, and Kings and Princes are ſo called in Holy Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. yet this acknowledgment muſt be made by us, and all Creatures; which was here openly declared by the two Tribes and half, and unanimouſly aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to by all the reſt, That there is <hi>one Sovereign Lord,</hi> The Lord God of gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he knows <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and independently, and not by Compariſon or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation;</hi> He knows <hi>intuitively, and not by the help of Reaſon or Diſcourſe, not by the aſſiſtance of Premiſſes or Concluſion.</hi> But this Divine Knowledge is too wonderful for us, it is ſo high we cannot attain unto it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.6. We may admire and adore, and we ought to do ſo, but we can never compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it; however the contemplation and adoration of this and all the other Attributes of God, as it is our buſineſs here on Earth, ſo 'twill be part of our happineſs in Heaven; <hi>where we ſhall know as we are known, where Faith will be conſummate in Viſion, and we ſhall ſee face to face.</hi> But in the <hi>interim</hi> we may make this good Uſe of God's Omniſcience and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence, to reſtrain our ſelves and others by it from open or ſecret ſins.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In vain (O Hypocrite!) doſt thou ſeek dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſolitude to conceal thy vice, and cover thy impiety, unleſs thou couldſt go where the Almighty ſees not, hide thy ſelf where his knowledge cannot reach, and fly from thine own Soul, thou canſt not be conceal'd from the All-ſeeing Eye of God, <hi>The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61759:7"/>
Lord God of gods, he knows;</hi> He knows what thou doſt in thy Cloſet, and ſecret Chambers, in thy ſilent and midnight Walks, and in thy moſt obſcure Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In vain (O Atheiſt!) doſt thou endeavour to baniſh God from all thy thoughts, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly imagine there is no ſuch vaſt and infinite Knowledge in the Moſt High: Do what thou canſt, the fear of the <hi>Almighty and inviſible Power</hi> will break in upon thee, and the dread of <hi>Divine Vengeance</hi> will overtake thee; eſpecially in times of publick calamity, or private diſtreſs: then notwithſtanding all thy ſottiſh Arts and methods to keep it off, thou wilt be haunted with the Apparition of a Deity, and the diſmal apprehenſions of a Judgment to come: then this ingenuous and open Confeſſion will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from thee, <hi>The Lord God of gods, he knows; He knows that I have been a great Sinner before him, and that I have no other way to eſcape his Juſtice, but by flying to his Mercy, that Mercy which I have hitherto abuſed and denied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In vain (O Rebel!) doſt thou go about to overturn and deſtroy that Government, which has hitherto preſerv'd thee; in vain endeavour to raiſe thy ſelf on thy Countries ruine, and Brethrens down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal; <hi>Thy Works of Darkneſs are brought to light, thy Myſtery of Iniquity revealed, and all thy Plots, which were laid as deep as Hell, are diſcovered by a Ray from Heaven,</hi> The Lord God of gods, he knows; <hi>He knows thy ſecret Clubs and cloſe Cabals: and though he may, and ſometimes does permit thy Twins of miſchief to come to the Birth; yet he will not ſuffer them to be delivered; but he has delivered us, and does, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we truſt he will ſtill deliver us.</hi> And ſo much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61759:7"/>
may ſuffice for the firſt Part of my Text, <hi>viz.</hi> a publick Declaration or Recognition of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power and Majeſty of God, that he is Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient and Omnipreſent, the ſupreme Lord, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Judge of the whole World. <hi>The Lord God of gods, the Lord God of gods, he knows;</hi> which is twice repeated, to make the more lively Impreſſion on us. I come now to the ſecond Part, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. A ſolemn Appeal to this Sovereign Lord and ſupreme Judge, for the Equity of their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; they deſire help, and expect deliverance from him upon theſe and no other terms, That they were not in Rebellion, nor tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>'Tis uſual with Good men, when their reputation is call'd in queſtion, and they are accus'd of ſome heavy crime, of which they are altogether innocent, to appeal to Heaven for an Evidence in their Cauſe, and ſolemnly to requeſt, that when men cannot, or will not, God himſelf would appear in their vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus when righteous <hi>Job</hi> was diſheartned by his beſt Friends, which ſhould have been his chiefeſt Comforters, and uncharitably charg'd by them for being a great Sinner, becauſe he had been a great Sufferer under the afflicting hand of God; he had no other way left to clear himſelf, but by calling on the Almighty, to teſtifie the integrity of his heart, and the innocency of his life, <hi>Job</hi> 16.19. <hi>Behold, my witneſs is in heaven, and my record is on high. Thus when pious</hi> David <hi>was ſlandered by reviling</hi> Shimei, <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for being a Murderer, a Man of Bloud, and charg'd with the death of</hi> Saul, <hi>and all his houſe, in whoſe ſtead he reigned,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7, 8. <hi>the only courſe he ſteer'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61759:8"/>
to take off this abominable imputation, was to refer his Cauſe to God, and to implore the Divine aſſiſtance to do him right,</hi> Pſalm 7.8, 10. <hi>Judge me, O Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my righteouſneſs, and according to my integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is in me; My defence is from God, who ſaveth the upright in heart.</hi> Thus when holy <hi>Paul</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed by falſe Teachers, that were then crept into the Corinthian Church, and miſrepreſented by them as one whoſe bodily preſence was weak, and ſpeech contemptible, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. as one that had taken but little pains in the Lord's Vineyard, which he was ſent to dreſs; to vindicate himſelf from this unjuſt calumny, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> thinks himſelf obliged to give them a ſhort Narrative of his labours, and travels in the Goſpel; which he does, Chap. 11. from ver. 21. to 30. and after the enumeration of ſeveral Particulars, makes this general Concluſion, <hi>That none of thoſe great Pretenders to the Chriſtian Religion had done and ſuffered ſo much for it, as he:</hi> And this he confirms by a moſt ſolemn Aſſeveration, wherein God is made a Party and a Judge, ver. 31. <hi>The God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, knoweth, that I lye not.</hi> And this is the reaſon why in our Courts of Juſtice, the Witneſſes that paſs betwixt man and man, and betwixt the King and the Priſoner at the Bar, are required to take a Corporal Oath, wherein they ſolemnly appeal to God for the truth of what they ſay, and tacitely imply, that they are ſo far from expecting God's help, that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate his wrath and vengeance upon themſelves, in caſe they ſwear falſely; <hi>So help me God.</hi> And this was the true cauſe why the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> make this ſolemn Appeal here in my Text, <hi>The Lord God of gods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61759:8"/>
knoweth:</hi> They were charged by their Brethren, the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the horrid crimes of Schiſm and Rebellion; with making a Schiſm in the Church, and a Rebellion in the State, <hi>(and the one is commonly a ſtep to the other, firſt a Schiſmatick, and next a Rebel)</hi> and thoſe that were their Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, to ſtrike the greater terrour and aſtoniſhment, did it with their Swords in their hands. Now to wipe off this harſh cenſure and ſevere reflection, which their uncharitable Brethren had paſs'd on them for erecting this new Altar; they all ſolemnly proteſt before God, That they did it in the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their hearts, and with no other deſign than to ſignifie to future Ages, that their Children and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children had a right to the Covenant God made with their Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> were Members of the ſame viſible Church, and Worſhippers of the ſame living God: They did not build it to offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, or to perform any other religious Service there; but barely as a Memorial, that they were of the ſame Extraction and Religion, as thoſe were that inhabited the Holy Land. And if this Anſwer did not ſatisfie, but they were reſolved to proceed to Acts of Hoſtility, and to make War upon them, they ſolemnly appeal to God to be the Umpire and Arbitrator betwixt them; and neither hoped for mercy or deliverance from their hands, in caſe their Apology were untrue, <hi>The Lord God of gods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he knows.</hi> And indeed the Event prov'd, that theſe <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> were in the right: For the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were immediately convinc'd that they had done nothing out of oppoſition to the Government, or diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Governours; and thereupon disbanded
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61759:9"/>
their Army, and bleſs'd the moſt high God that had kept them from deſtroying their innocent Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.32, 33.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt remark, That ſuch ſolemn appeals as theſe are then only lawful, when the Perſons are truly innocent that make them, and neceſſitated in their own defence to do it: and the inſtances I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gave you, were of ſuch men, their cauſe was juſt and good, and yet traduc'd as otherwiſe; and therefore they were not afraid ſolemnly to invite God to be a witneſs, and a Judge in it. And this will plainly appear by making a ſtricter inquiry into thoſe circumſtances theſe two Tribes and half were in, when this ſolemn Appeal was extorted from them: they were now on the other ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> where their great diſtance from <hi>Shiloh,</hi> together with their own ſtrength, being ſoon able to raiſe a conſiderable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of old experienc'd Souldiers, might eaſily have tempted them, (and not without proſpect of ſucceſs) to have endeavour'd an alteration of Government both in Church and State; eſpecially having ſo fair an opportunity to have done it, as their Brethrens being firſt in Arms afforded them; and they might have really pretended in their own juſtification, that they only undertook <hi>a defenſive War, (which was the falſe pretence of the old Rebels in Forty Two)</hi> and did but ſtand upon their own guard to hinder their Brethren from cutting their Throats. But they were ignorant of ſuch ſinful ſhifts and evaſions, in thoſe pure and elder times; and knowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Subjects (who by Gods own appointment ſucceeded <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Government of <hi>Iſrael) they knew it was unlawful upon any pretence whatſoever to reſiſt their Sovereign Prince:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61759:9"/>
inſtead of <hi>lifting up their Hands againſt him in a Warlike manner, they lift them up to Heaven in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and praying poſture, beſeeching, and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the God of it, to convince him of their innocence; and by that means to keep him from deſtroying them.</hi> This was really the caſe of the two Tribes and half; <hi>they did not under the greateſt provocation that could be, enter into a defenſive War, nor take any So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant</hi> to begin, and carry it on. But for men that by all the tyes of Nature, and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of ſacred Oaths, are bound to yield allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and ſubjection to their lawful King, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to <hi>Levy an Offenſive War againſt him,</hi> and to carry it on by the ſame ungodly and bloody means by which it was begun: for <hi>ſuch as theſe to appeal to Heaven for the juſtice of their Arms, and to challenge God to decide for them in the day of Battel, is ſuch a piece of arrogance and preſumption, as can ſcarce be parallell'd in all the Volumes of Antiquity. And yet this was the caſe of our late mad Reformers: They inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our Land, and made War upon their Lawful Prince, and ſo were Rebels; they traduc'd his Royal Perſon, and Government, and ſo were Slanderers; they deceiv'd the people with innumerable falſe ſtories and legendary tales, and ſo were Lyars; they rob'd, and plunderd their fellow-ſubjects of their proper Goods, and ſo were Thieves: and laſtly, they imbrued their hands in their Brethrens Blood, and ſo were Murderers. Yet theſe men, I ſay, had the forehead to conjure the God of Heaven, as their Arms were juſt, to give the Victory on their ſide. Good God! into what an age are we fallen, that can reconcile Paradoxes, and twiſt Contradictions!</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">That men ſhould be enemies to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, and yet endeavour to introduce it!
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61759:10"/>
that men ſhould advance the Glory of God, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Sacriledge! that men ſhould be the People of God, that by their works ſhew themſelves the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil, who was a Lyar, and Murderer from the beginning! And, laſtly, that men ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to fight for Religion, who really have none! Theſe are ſuch myſterious Riddles, as 'tis beyond the skill of an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to reſolve.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But poſſibly ſome of you may imagin this diſcourſe hath too much zeal and tranſport in it; yet I am confident that imagination will ſoon vaniſh, when you ſeriouſly conſider <hi>Gods honour</hi> is deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, and ſeems to lye at ſtake, being highly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted and abus'd by ſuch vile Hypocrites as theſe: and we know the meekeſt man upon earth grew angry and impatient, when he ſaw the Iſraelites worſhip, and dance before the <hi>Golden Calf, Exo.</hi> 32.19. and when we ſee the people running after <hi>ſuch another Idol, and falling down before it,</hi> 'tis high time to tell <hi>Judah</hi> of her ſins, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of her tranſgreſſions: <hi>And they, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear, (for they are a rebellious houſe) yet let them know there has been a Prophet among them,</hi> Ezek. 2.5. And truly without vanity I may ſay, I have faithfully diſcharg'd my duty in this particular, having often, and earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech'd you with abundance of arguments, and vehemence of ſpeech, to take heed of <hi>Rebellion which is as the ſin of Witchcraft;</hi> to beware of <hi>reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higher powers, for they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation;</hi> to lay to heart the character <hi>Jacob</hi> gives of his two ungodly children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5.6. <hi>Simeon and Levi are Brethren, inſtruments of cruelty are in their habitations; O my ſoul come not thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61759:10"/>
into their ſecret; unto their aſſembly mine honour be not thou united: for in their anger they would ſlay Kings, and dig down the walls of Church and State.</hi> Theſe things I have frequently inculcated, and preſs'd upon your conſciences, as you can all bear me witneſs, and I know I <hi>got ſome enemies by endeavouring to convince men of this great truth:</hi> but I verily believe they now wiſh they had taken my advice, which has been ſo often given them from this Sacred Place; <hi>and then all the ſpoil and plunder, the rapine and deſtruction, the wounds and bloodſhed which we ſo lately felt, might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily have been prevented;</hi> then they might have liv'd in peace, in their own houſes, with their own fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and under their own Vine and Fig-tree. <hi>But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not know in this their day the things that did belong to their peace, they are now therefore hid from their eyes,</hi> Luke 19.42. Now they muſt all put their hands upon their mouths, and confeſs, <hi>The Lord is juſt in all his ways and righteous in all his works; now they muſt acknowledg themſelves confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their own daring argument, and that their cauſe was bad, becauſe God did decide it againſt them in the day of Battel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the uſe I ſhall make of this ſecond part is this, To beg you to take heed of appealing to the great God to juſtify your unrighteous Deeds; To beware of Fathering the Works and Inventions of the Devil upon the God of Truth: This is a Sin of a monſtrous guilt, and prodigious magnitude, and if not the very ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, 'tis near of Kin to it; and certainly the very ſame that <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> did commit, when he gave out that himſelf was <hi>ſome great one; and what he did, though 'twas by the inſtigation of the Devil, to be done by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61759:11"/>
from God,</hi> Acts 8.9, 10. This ſin, I ſay, if not the ſame, is next to that which is unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> left that great Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor in a very doubtful and almoſt deſperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, affording him no other hopes or comfort but this, <hi>Perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee; perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterneſs, and bond of iniquity,</hi> ver. 22, 23. 'Tis a bold attempt to play with Lightning, or face the Thunder, or run upon a Cannons mouth ready to be diſcharged. <q rend="margQuotes">Tis more daring and dangerous to mock God, and gild the blackeſt Villanies with the ſpecious fringes of the glory of God, and the Proteſtant Religion: whereas the glory of God was never more ſullied, and the Proteſtant Religion never more barbarouſly handled, than in the Houſe of ſuch pretended Friends, who (as <hi>Brutus</hi> did <hi>Caeſar</hi>) have given it more mortal Wounds, than all its other Enemies round about. But ſuch Incendiaries as theſe, who bring unholy Fire to Gods Holy Altar, inſtead of burning that, muſt expect to periſh in the Flames, themſelves have kindled:</q> 
               <hi>For God will be ſanctified in them that come nigh him, and will be glorified before all the people,</hi> Lev. 5.3.</p>
            <p>And (my Brethren) 'tis fit God ſhould be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by us at this time; as for all his other mercies, ſo for that great mercy which we commemorate this day, and which comprehends ſo many under it, <q rend="margQuotes">no leſs than the entire defeat, and total overthrow of our implacable Enemies, whoſe tender mercies are cruel; no leſs than the preſervation of our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, and all his Loyal Subjects; of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties, our Lives and Fortunes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61759:11"/>
our Laws and Religion, from the hands of ſuch deſperate men as threatned to trample under feet, and quite deſtroy them.</q> For it has pleaſed God, and his Debtors we are for it, to croſs the bloody and treacherous deſigns of all thoſe who bare an ill will to our <hi>Sion;</hi> and to diſappoint the wicked and crafty devices of an <hi>aſpiring</hi> Abſolon, <hi>and conſpiring</hi> Achitophel, <hi>who impiouſly attempted to pull</hi> David <hi>from his Throne, and to lay his honour in the duſt:</hi> it has pleas'd Almighty God, (and we are ever bound to bleſs him for it, <hi>beyond the expectation of all, and the belief too of many</hi>) <q rend="margQuotes">to put a ſudden and happy end to a bloody and unnatural Rebellion, which might have been prolong'd for many Years, and waſted and worn us out to nothing, and at laſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the deſolation of our Country, and the tranſlation of our Kingdom into the hands of ſome Foreign Power. But in the midſt of theſe heavy Judgments God was pleas'd to remember mercy, and to think on the poor Church of <hi>England;</hi> which he has redeem'd of old, and ſo miraculouſly preſerv'd ever ſince the firſt happy Reformation, and to preſerve and continue us Members of the ſame; who after the manner which ſome call He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, and others Superſtition, ſo worſhip the God of our Fathers, <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14.</bibl>
               </q> So I paſs from the ſecond part, <hi>viz.</hi> the Solemn Appeal, to the third, which is,</p>
            <p n="3">III. The ſuppoſition, That if they were Rebels, or Tranſgreſſors againſt the Lord, that he would not ſave them, <hi>If it be in rebellion, or if in tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt the Lord, ſave us not this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two Tribes and half were ſo far convinc'd of the <hi>horrid Sin of Rebellion,</hi> whether it reſpect that which is made immediately againſt God, or that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61759:12"/>
which is rais'd againſt our lawful Prince; that if they had been guilty of either, they confeſs'd they deſerv'd no mercy from the hands of God or Man. And well might they think ſo, if we conſider the true nature of this ſin, and the indications of Gods wrath againſt it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we conſider the nature of Rebellion, as it immediately reſpects God, <hi>'tis a moſt enormous Crime, no leſs than an endeavour to pull the Almighty from his Throne, and ſeat our ſelves in it; to wreſt the Scepter out of his hand, and take it into ours: and in effect, and as far as man is able, to ungod the Deity.</hi> And this was <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s great ſin, too great to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, for which he was thrown from the higheſt Heaven into the loweſt Hell; he was for invading the incommunicable Attributes and Prerogatives of God, and for aſſuming that divine honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which can be imparted to no Creature whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as is plain from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13, 14. <hi>I will aſcend into Heaven, I will exalt my Throne above the Stars of God, I will aſcend above the heights of the Clouds, I will be like the moſt high:</hi> not like him in purity and holineſs, that he never aimed at; but in Dominion and Majeſty, and that caſt him into the bottomleſs Pit, and continues him there to the Judgment of the great day, <hi>Jude</hi> 6. And every wilful and preſumptuous Sinner is ſuch a kind of Rebel, though not to that unpardonable degree; his vitious Life is a perfect contradiction to Heaven, and an open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to him that made him; every ſin he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly commits, is as it were an Arrow ſhot againſt the Almighty, and an audacious attempt to deſtroy his very being; <hi>I will not allow the World to be made, govern'd, and judg'd by an All-wiſe and All-powerful
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61759:12"/>
God, nor ſubmit my ſelf to any of his Laws, to be rul'd and reſtrain'd by them; but am reſolv'd to live at large, and as looſly as I pleaſe; without God, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope in the World.</hi> This is the reſult of every obſtinate Offenders Diſcourſe; this the genuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of all his wicked actions.</p>
            <p>But beſides this Rebellion againſt God, there is another that comes but little ſhort of it, and that is Rebellion againſt our lawful Prince; and this too is a ſin of a deep dye, and a malignant nature; no leſs than an <hi>attempt to deface the Image, and reſiſt the Authority of God.</hi> For as Kings Reign by his Power, ſo they bear his ſtamp: and for Subjects to invade either, is in effect to offer violence to Heaven, and fight againſt God himſelf; as he that offers an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity to a Viceroy, does really affront the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign that deputed him. But the nature of this ſin will beſt appear by ſurveying ſome evil properties that belong to it, which are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt Rebellion contradicts the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion, and thwarts the practices of thoſe holy and inſpir'd men that firſt taught them; look over all the ſacred Books of the New Teſtament, and ſearch every Chapter and Verſe in it, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end, and I am confident you will find no one thing more inculcated than Obedience unto Sovereign Princes, and a quiet and peaceable ſubmiſſion to that Government under which we live; I am confident you will find no one thing more expreſly condemn'd, and ſeverely threatned, than reſiſting the higher Powers, and riſing up in Arms againſt them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c. Tit.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. and ſeveral other places, I have not now leiſure to name; and probably the reaſon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61759:13"/>
may be this, becauſe all the other duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern God, and our Neighbour, depend very much upon the regular adminiſtration of humane affairs, and the due ſubordination of Mankind one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and cannot poſſibly be perform'd without it. God cannot be ſerv'd, nor Man ſubſiſt and be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for as he ought, unleſs Government be ſecur'd: and that can never ſtand without this Doctrine of non-reſiſtance to ſupport it; take away this main Pillar, and humane Societies muſt diſſolve and fall to the ground: this no doubt was the reaſon why our Saviour and his Apoſtles have guarded the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Authority with ſo many poſitive Precepts, and fenc'd it with ſo many repeated Rules, as that there are ſcarce more about his own Divinity. And they were not like the antient Stoicks, men that only ſpoke great things, and did not do them; their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice was correſpondent to their Doctrine, and they maintain'd Paſſive Obedience by being themſelves the firſt Examples of it. Chriſt himſelf could have commanded <hi>Legions of Angels</hi> to his aſſiſtance, one of which had been ſtrong enough to have baffled and confounded all the <hi>Roman Legions;</hi> His Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles could have wrought innumerable Miracles, the leaſt of which might have reſcued them from the violent hands of <hi>Herod,</hi> or <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> of <hi>Nero,</hi> or <hi>Diocleſian: But they durſt not fetch Arms from Heaven to fight againſt the Lords Anointed; their Weapons were purely ſpiritual, even Prayers and Tears, the Spirit and Word of God, which in the hands of faithful Chriſtians are mighty to the pulling down the ſtrong holds of ſin,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4. and they renounced all Carnal Weapons, even Sword and Piſtol, Pike and Gun; which in the hands of Rebels ſerve only
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61759:13"/>
to ſet up Satans Kingdom, and enlarge the Devils Dominions. This was the temper of thoſe truly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and Apoſtolick Spirits; they took care to write after that fair Copy, the Prince of Peace had left them; and would (as he had done before them) <hi>rather part with all, even life it ſelf, than give the leaſt diſturbance to the State, or ſhew themſelves Enemies to</hi> Caeſar. <hi>And 'tis ſtrange that men ſhould fancy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſts Diſciples, and yet ſcorn to ſtoop ſo low as to take up their Croſs and follow him; 'tis ſtrange that men ſhould dream of reigning with Chriſt hereafter, that are not content to ſuffer with him here: yet ſuch ſtrange men are all Rebels, and ſo contrary is Rebellion to the Principles of Chriſtianity, and to the practices of the firſt and best Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Rebellion opens the Sluces of Impiety, and lets in a deluge of miſchiefs upon a Land; ſuch as Fire, Sword, and Famine; Rapes, Plunder and Murders; Spoils, Rapine, and Devaſtation. Theſe are ſome of the <hi>Black Retinue</hi> that wait upon <hi>this Cruel Maſter,</hi> (who like <hi>Beelzebub) has ſuch Fiends and Furies to attend him; creates a kind of Hell where e're he comes, and in a manner damns that place before the day of Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Rebellion deſtroys humane Societies, and puts Mankind into the ſame condition with wild Beaſts, making them to worry and devour each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſuch men will not be govern'd by Law, nor guided by reaſon, nor rul'd by Religion, but are deaf to thoſe, and hearken only to their boundleſs Appetites, and extravagant Luſts, and will act as theſe hurry them on, and not as the other do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them: <hi>In ſuch a caſe we ſhould always live in a perfect ſtate of War; the World it ſelf would be but a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61759:14"/>
greater humane Slaughter-Houſe, and mankind become ſo many Butchers to knock down and kill one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome ſprinklings of that deluge of wo which men bring upon themſelves and Country by Rebellion: and if my heart would ſerve me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the miſeries and Calamities of <hi>that</hi> which late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hapned <hi>here,</hi> and <hi>that other</hi> which broke out in <hi>forty one,</hi> and you would ſuffer your thoughts and meditations to dwell a while on both; I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent you would ingenuouſly confeſs, that not <hi>one half has</hi> been told you, and the <hi>whole can never be expreſs'd.</hi> And ſo much may ſuffice to ſhew you the nature of this horrid ſin, by the inſeparable proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that belong to it. I come next to treat of the indications of Gods wrath againſt it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, As for that Rebellion which immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſtrikes at God, and is rais'd againſt the Divine Majeſty; <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and his Sable Train are eternal Monuments of Gods heavy diſpleaſure againſt it; for their mutiny and inſurrection in Heaven, for their Rebellion and tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, they are condemn'd to the torments of Hell, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable pains of a ſad Eternity, <hi>Jude</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, As for that Rebellion which ſtrikes at Sovereign Princes, and is rais'd againſt their Royal Crown and Dignity, we have a convincing proof of Gods ſevere indignation againſt it, and that in an inſtance, which for the ſuddenneſs and dreadfulneſs of the puniſhment, is exactly parallel to it: for their murmuring and ſpeaking againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> who was the Ruler of that People, and but endeavouring to form a Rebellion againſt him, <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accomplices are ſwallowed up alive, and ſent quick to Hell, to ſuffer the vengeance of Eternal Fire, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.31,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61759:14"/>
32, 33. and God being of the ſame unchangeable nature, without doubt retains the ſame hatred to both ſorts of Rebels, and is as angry with them now as ever: and this he has abundantly teſtified, by ſhewing ſome viſible tokens of his diſpleaſure on them in all Ages, and puniſhing them with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and unuſual Death; as I could eaſily make out from innumerable Examples of the paſt and preſent times, but that I am loth to tire your patience in doing it. Let it ſuffice to inſtance in one more only, and him I can't omit, becauſe we have all ſeen him ſo exactly parallel'd in theſe dayes, <hi>and that is</hi> Abſolon, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>He was a beautiful, popular, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Prince;</hi> beautiful all acknowledge him to be, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.25. in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> there was none ſo much prais'd as <hi>Abſolon</hi> for his Beauty, from the ſoal of his Foot to the Crown of his Head there was no blemiſh in him; his complaiſant and cringing carriage ſhews him popular, he hugs, and careſſes, and kiſſes the meaneſt of the people, <hi>ch.</hi> 15.5, 6. and his ungrateful and unnatural demeanour towards his Royal Father <hi>David,</hi> ſpeaks him extremely ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious: For though he was once pardon'd his life, and before and after, the greateſt Favourite at Court, and, through that good King's exceſſive kindneſs, rais'd to be the ſecond man in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; yet this does not ſatisfie his aſpiring Soul. He is for being the firſt, and ſnatching the Crown from his Father's head, and that Crown too, which after his Father's death did not of Right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto him: and in order to it, he had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Conſults how to accompliſh his intended Treaſon, and at theſe Conſults crafty <hi>Achitophel</hi> was ſtill the chief, chap. 16.20. At laſt 'twas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61759:15"/>
That <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſhould cover his Rebellion with the ſpecious pretence of Religion, a Vizard which it often wears to hide its monſtrous defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, chap. 15.7, 8. But this Vizard was ſoon pluckt off, and <hi>Abſolon</hi> appear'd barefac'd at the Head of a great Army, who proclaim'd him King in <hi>Hebron:</hi> And this was done when there was another, better and rightful King in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and it was done by ſome of thoſe that either did, or pretended to follow him at firſt in the ſimplicity of their hearts, ver. 10, 11. to ſhew how eaſily men may paſs from the loweſt to the higheſt pitch of wickedneſs. And now 'twas time for <hi>David</hi> to arme againſt ſo formidable a Foe: and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly he does, dividing his Army into three Parts, with which he commanded his Generals to incloſe, and fight him, whilſt he himſelf unwillingly ſtaid at <hi>Manahim,</hi> to expect the iſſue of the Battel; and the Event was this, That <hi>Abſolon</hi>'s Army was all ſlain, and ſcattered, and he himſelf that was Head of it, though he eſcap'd a little while, and fled for his life, was afterwards diſmounted from the Mule he rode on, and ſeiz'd on in a Wood by the Kings Servants, and at laſt was put to death, by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Wounds, he receiving no leſs than three from <hi>Joab,</hi> and more from the hands of thoſe Ten young men that compas'd him about, and ſlew him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.14, 15. Thus fell the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and by the many fatal ſtrokes were given him, he ſeem'd to die more than once, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had been the death of ſo many, and ſhed ſo much innocent blood. Thus fell the ſhort-liv'd King, that was proclaim'd one day, and ſlain the next; and he fell in this exemplary and remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61759:15"/>
manner, becauſe he was a Rebel to his lawful Prince, <hi>If it be in Rebellion, or if in tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, ſave us not this day.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But here I muſt obſerve to you, that we are not always to judge of the goodneſs of a cauſe by the ſucceſs that may attend it: then Turks were more in the right than Chriſtians, the Bleſſed Jeſus muſt yield to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the Sacred Bible to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran; for that thoſe Infidels have been too victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and conquer'd and haraſs'd a great part of the Chriſtian world. For the moſt part indeed God blaſts ungodly Enterprizes in the very bud; or if he permits them to come to maturity, he meets with them at the long run by ſome ſad and fatal diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment even in this world; but this is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo, and this general rule (as all others) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of ſome exceptions: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Sometimes a good Prince is unproſperous in aſſerting his own undoubted Right, born down with the ſtream of unhappy and croſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, and at laſt comes to be impriſon'd and dye on a Scaffold. This, I ſay, ſometimes happens to a good Prince, to have a ſhort and troubleſom Reign, and in the end to be depos'd and murder'd;</hi> whilſt an ungodly and daring Uſurper ſteps into his Throne and reigns in peace, and dies in his bed. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Rebellion thrives, and Treaſon proſpers; and the uncircumciſed Philiſtins, profeſt Enemies to God and Goodneſs, prevail over his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and carry away the Ark in triumph, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.10, 11. and prophane it with their Heathen Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Idols, for the ſpace of twenty years: all which time the Church of God was under an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe; and his people being deſtitute of the Divine preſence and Worſhip, were in a cloudy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61759:16"/>
condition, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.2. <hi>And it came to paſs whilst the Ark abode in Kiriath-jearim, that the time was long; for it was twenty years: and all the houſe of Iſrael lamented after the Lord.</hi> But at laſt theſe days of mourning were over, and God cauſed the Ark to be brought back again, and plagued all thoſe that had a hand in taking, or keeping it away. And <hi>Iſrael</hi> was again bleſſed with their uſual victories and ſucceſs, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11. All which are ſuch plain Emblems of our troubles in Church and State, during the late Uſurpation, and of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py revolution that hapned afterwards, which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us once more upon the ſure foundations of peace and truth, that I need not ſpend time to draw the parallel, and make it plainer.</q> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of all is this, That if we look only on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of things, and no further, we may err in our judgment about them, and charge God fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the unequal diſtribution of them: but if we look forward, even to the final iſſue and event of things, when proſperous wickedneſs ſhall be cover'd with ſhame and confuſion, and afflicted piety lift up her head, and be circled with a Crown of Glory; then we ſhall abſolve Providence, and acknowledge that all the works of God are juſt and good; and that he will by no means condemn the righteous, or juſtifie the wicked, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.7.</p>
            <p>I come now briefly to apply the third and laſt Part, in drawing this Uſe or Inference from it: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of rebelling againſt God, or against Caeſar; They have both long hands, and will ſtrike ſure at laſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the blow be long a coming. Our God is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. and <hi>the wrath of a King is as Meſſengers of Death,</hi> ſays the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61759:16"/>
Wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.14. Take heed therefore of ſtirring up this fire, leſt it conſume thee; take heed of provoking this wrath, leſt the Meſſengers of Death lay hold on thee. For every mans experience may convince him of this Great Truth, That no Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon formed againſt God, or his Anointed, does ever proſper; but in the end cuts off thoſe Rebels that firſt formed it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.17. <hi>Survey the many broken Veſſels and ſhipwrack'd Tables, that every where float upon the Ocean of this World, and they all loudly proclaim to Standers-by, That they ſplit upon this very Rock; and call to them to avoid it with as much care and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, as they would a</hi> Scylla <hi>or</hi> Charybdis. <hi>Alas! how many Souls have fallen in, and periſhed in theſe Depths of Satan, and yet all the while thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure, and ſailing on towards the heighths of God, even the Haven of an happy Eternity? Wherefore, let others fatal miſcarriages ſet us right, and the Rocks on which they ſplit keep us from being caſt away.</hi> 'Tis dangerous, we ſay, to meddle with Edg-Tools, leſt they cut our Fingers; 'tis more dangerous to <hi>effront God, who can caſt Soul and Body into Hell-fire;</hi> or to <hi>oppoſe our lawful Sovereign,</hi> who may be truly ſtyl'd, <hi>A King of Miracles, as well as his deareſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the late King of Bleſſed Memory, to whom he ſeems to be an exact Parallel;</hi> ſo that we may truly ſay, what the Iſraelites did in the like caſe, <hi>When the Lord turned again the captivity of Sion,</hi> (and we were in a miſerable Captivity during the Rebels Domination here) <hi>we were like unto them that dream;</hi> We could ſcarce believe our own ſenſes, and that we were delivered from Captivity, when really it was ſo. And indeed ſo many miraculous circumſtances did concur in the bringing it to paſs, which I have not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61759:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
now time to enumerate, that we may truly ſay, This is the Finger of God, <hi>This has God done, and it is marvellous in our eyes,</hi> Pſal. 118.23. Marvellous, that ſo ſtrong an Army as the Rebels were, ſhould be ſo ſuddenly broken, and ſhattered to pieces; and that a handful of men ſhould do it! and therefore we may add that part of <hi>Deborah</hi>'s Song of Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for her Signal Victory over <hi>Siſera,</hi> Judg. 5.20, 31. <hi>They fought from heaven, the Stars in their courſes fought against</hi> the Rebels: <hi>So let all thine Enemies pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, O Lord; but let them that love him be as the Sun when he goeth forth in his might.</hi> I ſhall conclude my Diſcourſe on this Subject with that excellent counſel of <hi>Solomon,</hi> which I hope will now ſink down into your hearts, and for the future influence your whole lives and converſations; and that is, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21, 22. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with them that are given to change: for their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61759:17"/>
            <head>Sermons Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <list>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon of Temptation, before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon at the Act at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s <hi>Peculium Dei,</hi> before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s True Notion of Perſecution.</item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Moral <hi>Shechinah.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30.</item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon before the L. Mayor, at the <hi>Spittle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon at <hi>Worceſter, May</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Sermon at the <hi>York-ſhire</hi> Feaſt.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Sermon before the Houſe of Commons.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Duty and Happineſs of Doing Good.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Sermon at the Election of the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>May</hi> 29. 1682. before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9. 1683.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 30. 1683. before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi>'s Sermon <hi>September</hi> 2. 1684. before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Smith</hi>'s Sermon.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bisby</hi>'s Sermon, Proſecution no Perſecution.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bisby</hi>'s Modern Phariſees.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bisby</hi>'s Two Aſſize-Sermons.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Moore</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor, 1682.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Moore</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor, 1684.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Scot's</hi> Sermon before the Artillery Company.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s Sermon before the L. Mayor, <hi>Dec.</hi> 16. 1683.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s Sermon at Dr. <hi>Croun</hi>'s Funeral.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61759:18"/>Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s Sermon <hi>July</hi> 26. 1685.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s Aſſize-Sermon, at <hi>Chelmsford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lamb</hi>'s Sermon before the King at <hi>Windſor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lamb</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lamb</hi>'s Sermon, wherein the Liberty of Humane Nature is Stated, Diſcuſs'd and Limited.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wagſtaff</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9. 1685.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wagſtaff</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wagſtaff</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>July</hi> 26. 1685.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Viſitation-Sermon.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Sermon of Holy-days.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wray</hi>'s Sermon, The Rebellious City Deſtroy'd, <hi>September</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Loyalty proteſting againſt Popery, and Fanaticiſm Popiſhly affected.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Resberry</hi>'s Sermon at the <hi>Charter-Houſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Resberry</hi>'s Sermon at Sir <hi>Alan Broderick</hi>'s Funeral.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Payne</hi>'s Sermon at the <hi>Brentwood</hi>-Feaſt.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Payne</hi>'s Sermon <hi>September</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Milbourne</hi>'s Original of Rebellion, Preached <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 30.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Milbourne</hi>'s Sermon <hi>September</hi> 9. 1683.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Battel</hi>'s Aſſize-Sermon at <hi>Hertford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi>'s Sermon of the Keeping of Holy-Days, Preached before the Right Reverend the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Grail</hi>'s Four Sermons:
<list>
                     <item>I. Of True Reformation of Our Selves.</item>
                     <item>II. Of Pious Reverence towards God and the King.</item>
                     <item>III. Of Juſt Abhorrence of Uſurping Republicans.</item>
                     <item>IV. Of Due Affection to the Monarchy.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Gaſcarth</hi>'s Sermon at Duke <hi>Lauderdale</hi> Funeral.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Holland</hi>'s Aſſize-Sermon.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61759:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
